So whenever I visit a school and talk to students,
في كل مرّة أزور مدرسةً و أتكلم مع الطلاب،
I always ask them the same thing:
أسألهم دائمًا نفس السؤال:
Why do you Google?
لماذا تبحث في غوغل؟
Why is Google the search engine of choice for you?
لماذا غوغل هو محرك البحث المختار من قبلك؟
Strangely enough, I always get the same three answers.
الغريب، أنني دائمًا أحصل على نفس الأجوبة الثلاثة.
One, "Because it works,"
الأول, "لأنه يعمل،"
which is a great answer; that's why I Google, too.
إنه جوابٌ عظيم؛ لهذا أنا أبحث في غوغل، أيضًا.
Two, somebody will say,
الثاني، أحدهم يقول،
"I really don't know of any alternatives."
"أنا لا أعرف أي بديل في الحقيقة."
It's not an equally great answer and my reply to that is usually,
إنه ليس بجواب رائعٍ على حدٍ سواء و ردي في العادة يكون،
"Try to Google the word 'search engine,'
"جرّب البحث في غوغل عن كلمة 'محرك بحث،'
you may find a couple of interesting alternatives."
قد تجد بضع بدائل مثيرة للإعجاب."
And last but not least, thirdly,
و الأخر و ليس الأخير، ثالثًا،
inevitably, one student will raise her or his hand and say,
حتمًا، أحد الطلاب سيرفع أو ترفع يدها و يقول،
"With Google, I'm certain to always get the best, unbiased search result."
"مع غوغل، أنا متأكد أني سأجد الأفضل، نتائج بحث موضوعية."
Certain to always get the best, unbiased search result.
متأكد دائمًأ بالحصول على الأفضل، نتائج بحث موضوعية.
Now, as a man of the humanities,
الآن، كرجل علوم إنسانية
albeit a digital humanities man,
و إن كان بشكلٍ رقمي،
that just makes my skin curl,
هذا يجعل جسدي يقشعّر،
even if I, too, realize that that trust, that idea of the unbiased search result
حتى لو كنت أنا أيضّا، أدرك أن هذه الثقة، أن فكرة نتائج البحث الموضوعية
is a cornerstone in our collective love for and appreciation of Google.
هي حجز الزاوية لحبنا أجمعين و تقديرنا لغوغل.
I will show you why that, philosophically, is almost an impossibility.
سأريكم لماذا، فلسفيًا، هو استحالة تقريبًا.
But let me first elaborate, just a little bit, on a basic principle
ولكن اسمحوا لي أن أعرج أولا، قليلًا فقط، على مبدأ أساسي
behind each search query that we sometimes seem to forget.
و هو أننا عند كل طلب بحث أحيانًا ننسى.
So whenever you set out to Google something,
لذا، كل ما شرعت بالبحث عن شيء عن طريق غوغل،
start by asking yourself this: "Am I looking for an isolated fact?"
ابدأ بسؤال نفسك التالي: "هل أبحث عن حقيقة معزولة؟"
What is the capital of France?
ما هي عاصمة فرنسا؟
What are the building blocks of a water molecule?
ما هي المكونات الأساسية لجزيء الماء؟
Great -- Google away.
عظيم -- غوغل خارج الحساب.
There's not a group of scientists who are this close to proving
ليس هناك مجموعة من العلماء قريبون لهذه الدرجة من إثبات
that it's actually London and H30.
أته في الحقيقة لندن و H3O.
You don't see a big conspiracy among those things.
لاترى مؤامرةً كبيرةً بين هذه الأشياء.
We agree, on a global scale,
نحن نتفق، على مستوى عالمي،
what the answers are to these isolated facts.
حول الأجوبة بالنسبة إلى هذه الحقائق المعزولة.
But if you complicate your question just a little bit and ask something like,
لكن عندما تعقّد سؤالك قليلًا فقط و تسأل شيئًا من هذا القبيل،
"Why is there an Israeli-Palestine conflict?"
"لماذا هناك صراع اسرائيلي-فلسطيني؟"
You're not exactly looking for a singular fact anymore,
إنك لم تعد تبحث عن حقيقة مفردة بعد الآن،
you're looking for knowledge,
إنك تبحث عن المعرفة،
which is something way more complicated and delicate.
التي تكون شيئًا أعقد بكثير و حساسًا أكثر.
And to get to knowledge,
و للحصول على المعرفة،
you have to bring 10 or 20 or 100 facts to the table
عليك بجلب 10 أو 20 أو 100 حقيقىة على الطاولة
and acknowledge them and say, "Yes, these are all true."
و الاعتراف بها و قول، "نعم، كل هذا هو الحقيقة."
But because of who I am,
و لكن بسبب كوني أنا،
young or old, black or white, gay or straight,
شابا أو عجوزا ، أسود أو أبيض، مثليا أو عاديا ،
I will value them differently.
سأقيمها بشكلٍ مختلف،
And I will say, "Yes, this is true,
و سأقول، "نعم، هذا صحيح،
but this is more important to me than that."
و لكن هذا مهمٌ بالنسبة إلي أكثر من هذا."
And this is where it becomes interesting,
و هنا يصبح الأمر مثيرًا،
because this is where we become human.
لأننا هنا نصبح إنسانيين.
This is when we start to argue, to form society.
هنا حيث نبدأ بالنقاش، لتشكيل مجتمع.
And to really get somewhere, we need to filter all our facts here,
و لنصل حقيقةً إلى مكانٍ ما، نحتاج إلى تصفية جميع الحقائق هنا،
through friends and neighbors and parents and children
من خلال الأصدقاء و الجيران و الأهل و الأطفال
and coworkers and newspapers and magazines,
و شركاء العمل و الجرائد و المجلات،
to finally be grounded in real knowledge,
لنستند في النهاية إلى حقيقة حقيقية،
which is something that a search engine is a poor help to achieve.
التي تكون شيئًا تضعف محركات البحث في المساعدة على تحقيقه.
So, I promised you an example just to show you why it's so hard
لذا، لقد وعدتكم بمثال فقظ لأريكم لماذا هو من الصعوبة بمكان
to get to the point of true, clean, objective knowledge --
الوصول إلى نقظة المعرفة الخالصة، الموضوعية --
as food for thought.
كغذاء للفكر.
I will conduct a couple of simple queries, search queries.
سوف أجري بضعةً من الاستفسارات، و الاستعلامات البسيطة.
We'll start with "Michelle Obama,"
سوف نبدأ ب "ميشيل أوباما,"
the First Lady of the United States.
السيدة الأولى للولايات المتحدة.
And we'll click for pictures.
و سوف ننقر على صور.
It works really well, as you can see.
إنها تجري جيدًا، كما ترون.
It's a perfect search result, more or less.
إنها نتائج بحثٍ ممتازة، تقريبًا.
It's just her in the picture, not even the President.
إنها هي فقط في الصورة، و لا حتى الرئيس معها.
How does this work?
كيف يحدث هذا؟
Quite simple.
ببساطة شديدة.
Google uses a lot of smartness to achieve this, but quite simply,
يستعمل غوغل بعض الذكاء لإكمال هذا، و لكن ببساطة شديدة،
they look at two things more than anything.
إنهم ينطرون إلى شيئين أكثر من أي شيءٍ.
First, what does it say in the caption under the picture on each website?
أولًا، ماذا تقول التسمية التوضيحية تحت الصورة تحت كل موقع؟
Does it say "Michelle Obama" under the picture?
هل تقول "ميشيل أوباما" تحت الصورة؟
Pretty good indication it's actually her on there.
مؤشر جيد جدًا إنها هي في الحقيقة.
Second, Google looks at the picture file,
ثانيًا، ينظر غوغل إلى ملف الصورة،
the name of the file as such uploaded to the website.
اسم الملف كما هو مرفوعٌ على الموقع.
Again, is it called "MichelleObama.jpeg"?
مرة أخرى، هل يدعى "مشيل أوباما.jpeg"؟
Pretty good indication it's not Clint Eastwood in the picture.
مؤشرٌ جيدٌ جدًا إنها ليست صورة كلينت إيستوود.
So, you've got those two and you get a search result like this -- almost.
إذًا، لديك هذين الاثنين و ستحصل على نتائج بحثٍ كهذه -- تقريبًا.
Now, in 2009, Michelle Obama was the victim of a racist campaign,
الآن، في 2009، كانت ميشيل أوباما ضحيةً لحملةٍ عنصرية،
where people set out to insult her through her search results.
حيث قام الناس بإهانتها من خلال نتائج البحث.
There was a picture distributed widely over the Internet
كان هناك صورةٌ قد انتشرت بشكلٍ كبيرٍ في الانترنت
where her face was distorted to look like a monkey.
حيث تم تشويه وجهها لتشبه قردًا.
And that picture was published all over.
و تم نشر هذه الصورة في كل مكان.
And people published it very, very purposefully,
و نشرها الناس بشكلٍ مقصودٍ بقوة،
to get it up there in the search results.
لوضعها هناك في نتائج البحث.
They made sure to write "Michelle Obama" in the caption
تأكدوا من كتابة "ميشيل أوباما" في التسمية التوضيحية
and they made sure to upload the picture as "MichelleObama.jpeg," or the like.
و تأكدوا من رفع الصورة تحت مسمى "ميشيل أوباما.jpeg"، أو ما شابه ذلك.
You get why -- to manipulate the search result.
سترى لماذا -- للتلاعب في نتائج البحث.
And it worked, too.
و قد نجحت أيضًا.
So when you picture-Googled for "Michelle Obama" in 2009,
لذا عندما بحثت في غوغل عن صورة "ميشيل أوباما" عام 2009،
that distorted monkey picture showed up among the first results.
ظهرت صورة القرد المشوه في الأعلى بين النتائج الأولى.
Now, the results are self-cleansing,
الآن، النتائج تتصفى بنفسها،
and that's sort of the beauty of it,
و هنا تكمن جماليتها،
because Google measures relevance every hour, every day.
لأن معايير غوغل تتلائم كل ساعة، كل يوم.
However, Google didn't settle for that this time,
و مع ذلك، لم يقم غوغل بتسوية هذا هذه المرّة،
they just thought, "That's racist and it's a bad search result
فقط فكروا، " هذا عنصري و هي نتائج بحثٍ سيئة
and we're going to go back and clean that up manually.
و سوف نقوم بالعودة و مسحها يدويًا.
We are going to write some code and fix it,"
سنقوم بكتابة بعض الأكواد لإصلاحها،"
which they did.
الأمر الذي فعلوه.
And I don't think anyone in this room thinks that was a bad idea.
و لا أعتقد أن أي أحدٍ في هذه القاعة يعتقد بأنها فكرةٌ سيئة.
Me neither.
و لا أنا أيضًا.
But then, a couple of years go by,
لكن بعدها، تمر بضعة سنين،
and the world's most-Googled Anders,
و يصبح أكثر بحثٍ على غوغل هو اندرش،
Anders Behring Breivik,
اندرش بهرنغ بريفيك،
did what he did.
فعل ما فعله.
This is July 22 in 2011,
هذا في 22 يوليو "تموز" عام 2011،
and a terrible day in Norwegian history.
و هو يومٌ فظيع في تاريخ النرويج.
This man, a terrorist, blew up a couple of government buildings
هذا الرجل، إرهابي، فجّر بضع مبانٍ حكوميةٍ
walking distance from where we are right now in Oslo, Norway
على بعد مرمى حجر من مكاننا هنا الآن في أوسلو، النرويج
and then he traveled to the island of Utøya
و سافر بعدها إلى جزيرة أوتويا
and shot and killed a group of kids.
و رمى الرصاص و قتل مجموعةً من الأطفال.
Almost 80 people died that day.
مات تقريبًا 80 شخصًا ذلك اليوم.
And a lot of people would describe this act of terror as two steps,
و يصف الكثير من الأشخاص هذا العمل الإرهابي في خطوتين،
that he did two things: he blew up the buildings and he shot those kids.
أنه فعل شيئين: فجّر المباني و قتل الأطفال.
It's not true.
هذا ليس بصحيح.
It was three steps.
لقد كانت ثلاثة خطوات.
He blew up those buildings, he shot those kids,
فجّر تلك المباني و قتل أولئك الأطفال،
and he sat down and waited for the world to Google him.
و جلس و انتظر العالم ليبحثوا عنه في غوغل.
And he prepared all three steps equally well.
و قد جهّز الخطوات الثلاث بدقة متساوية.
And if there was somebody who immediately understood this,
و إذ كان هناك شخصٌ قد فهم فورًا هذا،
it was a Swedish web developer,
كان مطور انترنت سويدي،
a search engine optimization expert in Stockholm, named Nikke Lindqvist.
خبير محرك البحث الأمثل في ستوكهولم يسمى، نيكي لينكفيست.
He's also a very political guy
و هو شخصٌ سياسيٌ جدًا
and he was right out there in social media, on his blog and Facebook.
و كان حاضرا تمامًا في وسائل التواصل، و مدونته و الفيسبوك.
And he told everybody,
و أخبر الجميع،
"If there's something that this guy wants right now,
"لو كان هناك شيءٌ يريده هذا الشخص الآن،
it's to control the image of himself.
هو سيطرته على صورته.
Let's see if we can distort that.
فلنر إن كنا نستطيع تشويه هذا.
Let's see if we, in the civilized world, can protest against what he did
فلنر إن كنا، في العالم المتحضّر، نستطيع التظاهر ضد ما فعله
through insulting him in his search results."
من خلال إهانته في نتائج البحث."
And how?
و كيف؟
He told all of his readers the following,
أخبر جميع قرائه و متابعيه،
"Go out there on the Internet,
"اذهبوا إلى شبكة الانترنت،
find pictures of dog poop on sidewalks --
جدوا صورًا لفضلات كلب على الأرصفة --
publish them in your feeds, on your websites, on your blogs.
انشروها في مغذيات أخباركم، و على مواقعكم، و مدونتاكم.
Make sure to write the terrorist's name in the caption,
تأكدوا من كتابة اسم الإرهابي في التسمية التوضيحية،
make sure to name the picture file "Breivik.jpeg."
تاكدوا من تسمية ملف الصورة "بريفيك.jpeg."
Let's teach Google that that's the face of the terrorist."
دعونا نعلّم غوغل أن هذا هو وجه الإرهابي."
And it worked.
و قد نجحت الخطة.
Two years after that campaign against Michelle Obama,
بعد عامين من الحملة ضد ميشيل أوباما،
this manipulation campaign against Anders Behring Breivik worked.
كانت حملة التشويه ضد أندرش بيهرينغ بريفيك قد نجحت.
If you picture-Googled for him weeks after the July 22 events from Sweden,
إن كنت تبحث عنه في صور غوغل بعد أسابيع من حدث 22 يوليو في السويد،
you'd see that picture of dog poop high up in the search results,
فستجد صورًا لفضلات كلب قد اعتلت نتائج البحث،
as a little protest.
كاحتجاجٍ بسيط.
Strangely enough, Google didn't intervene this time.
بشكلٍ غريب، لم يتدخل غوغل هذه المرّة.
They did not step in and manually clean those search results up.
لم يتدخلوا و يحذفوا يدويًا نتائج البحث العليا تلك.
So the million-dollar question,
لذا، سؤال المليون دولار،
is there anything different between these two happenings here?
هل هناك أي فرقٍ بين هذين الحدثين هنا؟
Is there anything different between what happened to Michelle Obama
هل هناك أي شيءٍ مختلف بين ما حصل مع ميشيل أوباما
and what happened to Anders Behring Breivik?
و ما حدث مع أندرش بهرينغ بريفيك؟
Of course not.
بالطبع لا.
It's the exact same thing,
إنه نفس الشيء تمامًا،
yet Google intervened in one case and not in the other.
و مع ذلك تدخل غوغل في قضيةٍ و لم يتدخل في الأخرى .
Why?
لماذا؟
Because Michelle Obama is an honorable person, that's why,
لأن ميشيل أوباما شخصيةٌ مرموقة، لهذا السبب،
and Anders Behring Breivik is a despicable person.
و أندرش بهرينغ بريفيك شخصٌ دنيء.
See what happens there?
إذًا ما الذي يحصل هنا؟
An evaluation of a person takes place
تقييم شخصٍ ما يؤخذ بعين الاعتبار
and there's only one power-player in the world
و هناك لاعبٌ قوي في العالم
with the authority to say who's who.
مع صلاحية القول لتحديد من يكون.
"We like you, we dislike you.
"أنت تعجبنا، أنت لا تعجبنا.
We believe in you, we don't believe in you.
نحن نثق بك، نحن لا نثق بك.
You're right, you're wrong. You're true, you're false.
أنت على حق، لست على حق. أنت حقيقي، أنت مزيف.
You're Obama, and you're Breivik."
أنت أوباما،و أنت بريفيك."
That's power if I ever saw it.
هذه هي القوة بعينها.
So I'm asking you to remember that behind every algorithm
لذا أطلب منكم أن تتذكروا أن وراء كل خوارزمية
is always a person,
دائمًا هناك شخصٌ،
a person with a set of personal beliefs
شخصٌ معدٌّ بمعتقداتٍ شخصيةٍ
that no code can ever completely eradicate.
حيث لا يمكن لأي شيفرة أن تقضي عليها تمامًا.
And my message goes out not only to Google,
و توجَّه رسالتي ليس فقط إلى غوغل،
but to all believers in the faith of code around the world.
بل إلى كل المؤمنين بقدرة الشيفرات حول العالم.
You need to identify your own personal bias.
عليك تحديد الانحياز الشخصي الخاص بك.
You need to understand that you are human
عليك أن تفهم أنك بشر
and take responsibility accordingly.
وتحمل المسؤولية وفقًا لذلك.
And I say this because I believe we've reached a point in time
و أقول هذا لأتي أعتقد اننا قد وصلنا إلى نقطة في وقتنا
when it's absolutely imperative
وهي أنه أصبح من الضروري للغاية
that we tie those bonds together again, tighter:
أن نربط هذين الحبلين سويًا مرة أخرى، بشكلٍ محكم:
the humanities and the technology.
وهما الإنسانية و التكنولوجيا.
Tighter than ever.
بشكلٍ محكمٍ أكثر من أي وقت.
And, if nothing else, to remind us that that wonderfully seductive idea
و، إن كان هناك أي شيءٍ آخر، ليذكرنا أن هذه الفكرة الرائعة و المغرية
of the unbiased, clean search result
حول نتائج البحث، النظيفة و الغير منحازة
is, and is likely to remain, a myth.
فهو أن تظل أسطورة.
Thank you for your time.
شكرًا لوقتكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)